Guide to the Ernest Becker Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Ernest Becker papers,
1952-1977
[Bulk Dates: 1962-1974]
Becker, Ernest.
8.34 linear ft. ( 2 document boxes, 5 notecard boxes, and 2 record storage cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS# 1567
6909763
Becker’s papers consist primarily of correspondence and notes on cultural anthropology, sociology, and psychology. Boxes of notecards and annotated books are also included in the collection.
Biographical Note
Ernest Becker was born in Springfield, MA in 1924. He served in World War II and shortly afterwards, attended Syracuse University in New York. In his early 30s, he pursued a graduate degree in cultural anthropology at his alma mater. He received his Ph.D. in 1960, and soon after, became a professor at Simon Fraser University in Vancouver, BC, Canada. His main interest was in philosophical anthropology-relating to the interdisciplinary and cross-cultural approach to the study of human beings.
Becker was the author of several books. His topics included the science of man, mental illness, and the fear of death, Two months after his passing, he won the Pulitzer Prize for non-fiction for his book, The Denial of Death.
He was married to Marie H. Becker. In late 1972, he was diagnosed with colon cancer and died in March 1974 at the age of 49.
Scope and Content
The collection contains many of Becker's notes and lectures on cultural anthropology, sociology, psychiatry, and psychology. His correspondence consists of letters to close friends, and colleagues about his works, as well as letters to potential publishers. His observations, notes and lectures are typed on notecards along with related newspaper clippings. He also recorded his thoughts on the inside covers and the first few pages of various books. There are also two personal journals from the 1950s.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1966-1974
Series II: Published Materials, 1962-1977
Series III: Academic Materials, 1958-1973
Series IV: Personal Materials, 1958-1973
Series V: Research Notecards, 1966-1970
Series VI: Annotated Books, 1915-1968
Subjects
Becker, Ernest; Becker, Ernest--Denial of Death
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Marie H. Becker Gift 2004 M2003-2004-443
Selected Related Material-- at Columbia
Otto Rank Papers, Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1966-1974
  In this series, there are letters between Becker and his friends and colleagues in the academic field and in the publishing arena.
  - Letters from or to Ernest Becker, 1966-1974 (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 3)
  - Letters Regarding Albion Small, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Published Materials, 1962-1977
  This series contains correspondence and published reviews related to his various books.
  - Correspondence and Reviews
    - Angels in Armor, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Beyond Alienation, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Birth and Death of Meaning, 1962-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Denial of Death, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lost Science of Man, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Revolution in Psychiatry, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Structure of Evil, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Book Reviews
    - The Imperial Animal, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Zen: A Rational Critique, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Published Articles, 1962-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III: Academic Materials, 1958-1973
  This series consists of Becker’s lectures, notes, semester schedules, course outlines, and reading lists.
  - Lecture on the History of the Human Sciences, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notes on Anthropology, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Course Outlines, Semester Schedules, and Reading Lists, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Personal Materials, 1958-1973
  This series contains Becker’s bound journals from the 1950s, a typed biography and personal journal, and resumé.
  - Becker’s Biography and Resume, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Private Journals, 1952-1958 (2 bound journals, unfoldered) (Box 2)
  - Private Journal Duplicates, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series V: Research Notecards, 1966-1972 (5 Notecard Boxes)
  This series consists of Becker’s typed, 3 x 5 notecards detailing his cultural anthropological observations along with some newspaper clippings. There are also notes about mental illness, history of disease, origins of social evils, the purpose of culture, and abstract concepts of sociology.
  - Photocopies of Newspaper Clippings (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notes on Education on Mental Illness, Denial of Animality, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Lectures at UC Berkeley, CA on Theology, Evil, and Social History, 1966-1972 (Box 4)
  - Lectures at UC Berkeley, CA on the Problem of Human Nature, 1967? (Box 5)
  - Notes on Social Evil: Origins of Inequality and Facism, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Notes on Anthropology, Sociology, Purpose of Culture and Abstract Concepts of Sociology, 1968-1970 (Box 7)
- Series VI: Annotated Books, 1915-1968 (2 record storage cartons) (Box 8-9)
  This series consists primarily of books that contain annotations by Becker.